# SARANSH CHOPRA

🏶 saransh-cpp.github.io | 🗷 saransh0701@gmail.com | 🛅 saransh-cpp | 🗘 Saransh-cpp | 📢 WhiteViolin

#### About

Saransh is an engineering junior who, by day, works on his academic and professional commitments, and by night, develops and maintains open-source research software, which he believes are the key to collaborative and reproducible research.

He is passionate about Research Software Engineering, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Scientific Machine Learning, and Open-Source Research Software.

#### Education

#### Cluster Innovation Centre, University of Delhi

New Delhi, India

Major: Information Technology and Mathematical Innovations

2020 - 2024

 ${\it Minor: Computational Biology}$ 

CGPA 9.46

# Research and Work Experience

#### FluxML, The Julia Programming Language

Remote

Open-source developer and technical writer [Funded by The Julia Programming Language]

May 2022 - Present

Mr. Dhairya Gandhi (Julia Computing)

- Fixing bugs and developing the infrastructure of prominent Julia ML and DL libraries such as Flux.jl (3,700+ stars), NNlib.jl (Neural Network primitives 150+ stars), Metalhead.jl (Computer vision models 270+ stars), and Functors.jl.
- Writing original Machine Learning/Deep Learning tutorials, documentation and API references for FluxML's ecosystem.
- Working closely with doctoral researchers and FluxML maintainers from around the world.

# Institute for Research and Innovation in Software for High Energy Physics, (IRIS-HEP), Princeton University

Remote

IRIS-HEP research fellow [Funded by IRIS-HEP]

June 2022 - September 2022

Dr. Henry Schreiner (Princeton University / CERN) and Dr. Jim Pivarski (Princeton University)

- Prepared Vector (72,000+ installs 40+ stars) for v0.9.0, v0.10.0, and v1.0.0 (first major release) by developing new public API, fixing bugs, and building new infrastructure.
- The releases are currently being used by researchers at CERN, ATLAS, CMS, and Princeton University to construct 4D jagged (awkward) vectors and perform Just-In-Time compiled vector operations in Python.
- Worked closely with CERN and Princeton researchers to build infrastructures for the HEP ecosystem.

#### PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling), NumFOCUS

Remote

Google Summer of Code student developer [Funded by Google]

May 2021 - August 2021

Dr. Valentin Sulzer (Carnegie Melon University), Dr. Robert Timms (University of Oxford), Dr. Ferran Brosa Planella (University of Warwick)

- Built an automated Twitter Bot capable of constructing Mathematical Simulations of Batteries, including but not limited to different battery models, parameter sets, chemistries, degradation modes, and experiments.
- Developed a replying functionality to run Mathematical Simulations on command, created a CI/CD pipeline, and followed a micro-services-based architecture.
- Worked closely with post-doctoral research fellows and PyBaMM maintainers from around the world.

#### **Publications**

[Tra+21] T. G. Tranter, R. Timms, V. Sulzer, F. B. Planella, G. M. Wiggins, S. V. Karra, P. Agarwal, S. Chopra, S. Allu, P. R. Shearing, and D. J. L. Brett. *liionpack: A Python package for simulating packs of batteries with PyBaMM*. Journal of Open Source Software, 7(70), 4051. Oct. 2021. DOI: https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.04051.

# Open Source Research Software

#### **PyBaMM**

Maintainer and Core Developer - 215,000+ installs - 420+ stars

PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling) solves physics-based electrochemical DAE models by using state-of-the-art automatic differentiation and numerical solvers.

Vector

 $Maintainer\ and\ Core\ Developer\ \text{--}\ 72,000+\ installs\ \text{--}\ 40+\ stars$ 

Vector is a Python 3.6+ library for 2D, 3D, and Lorentz vectors, especially arrays of vectors, to solve common physics problems in a NumPy-like way.

[SSP] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. *Vector: vector classes and utilities.* DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.5942082. URL: https://github.com/scikit-hep/vector.

Flux.jl

 $Core\ contributor\ -\ 80,000+\ installs\ -\ 3,700+\ stars$ 

August 2016

Flux is an elegant approach to machine learning. It's a 100% pure-Julia stack, and provides lightweight abstractions on top of Julia's native GPU and AD support. Flux makes the easy things easy while remaining fully hackable.

**BattBot** 

Maintainer and Core Developer - 130+ followers - 10+ stars

An automated Twitter Bot that Tweets random Battery Mathematical Modeling Simulations and replies to the requested Battery Simulations.

liionpack

 $Maintainer\ and\ Core\ Developer$  - 2,000+ installs - 30+ stars

liionpack takes a 1D PyBaMM model and makes it into a pack. You can either specify the configuration e.g. 16 cells in parallel and 2 in series (16p2s) or load a netlist.

#### Other notable contributions

- **DeepXDE**: DeepXDE is a library for scientific machine learning 330,000+ installs 1,200+ stars Implemented utility functions and improved the existing examples on solving partial differential equations using Physics-Informed neural networks.
- $\circ$  Colour: Colour Science for Python 6,000,000+ installs 1,500+ stars Implemented the conversion between RGB and HCL colourspaces.
- Scikit-HEP ecosystem: High Energy Physics in Python
  Fixed minor bugs in awkward and hist, added support for coverage in cookie, and wrote new developer pages.

# Posters and Presentations

- [SSP22a] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Compiling Awkward Lorentz vectors with Numba. 21st International Workshop on Advanced Computing and Analysis Techniques in Physics Research (ACAT). Poster (upcoming). Oct. 2022. URL: https://indi.to/45Kzq.
- [SSP22b] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Constructing HEP vectors and analyzing HEP data using Vector. 5th International Workshop on Python in High-Energy-Physics (PyHEP). Presentation. Oct. 2022. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7067310. URL: https://indi.to/bPmMc.
- [S C22a] S. Chopra. Python packaging: from stone age to the future. PyDelhi workshop. Presentation. Sept. 2022.
- [S C22b] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 10th Annual Conference on Python Asia-Pacific (PyCon APAC). Presentation. Sept. 2022. URL: https://tw.pycon.org/2022/en-us/conference/talk/243.
- [S C22c] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 21st Annual Conference On Python Europe (EuroPython). Presentation. July 2022. URL: https://ep2022.europython.eu/session/code-coverage-through-unit-tests-running-in-sub-processes-threads-locally-and-automated-on-github.
- [S C22d] S. Chopra. Vector Constructors, documentation, and benchmarks. IRIS-HEP Lightning Talks. Presentation. June 2022. URL: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fLt7BHuASpw.
- [S C21] S. Chopra. BattBot: Mathematical Modeling of Batteries using an automated Twitter bot. 1st International Training Workshop on Python Battery Mathematical Modeling (PyBaMM). Presentation. Oct. 2021. URL: https://www.pybamm.org/training.

#### Grants, Prizes and Achievements

observatory

o PyCon Acia-Pacific (APAC)'s grant to lead a talk virtually (NT\$3,600)	July 2022
$\circ$ Shubhra Kar Linux Foundation Training Scholarship (500 recipients worldwide) for contributions to open-source research software (\$695)	June 2022
$\circ$ Euro Python's travel grant to lead a talk in-person (£460)	$June\ 2022$
$\circ$ PyCon Italia's travel grant to lead a workshop in-person (£400 + lodging support)	$April\ 2022$
$\circ$ Faraday Institution's Collaboration Award for contributions to the PyBaMM ecosystem	$November\ 2021$
$\circ$ Won the Elastic hackathon (out of 2500+ registrations) with a Flutter-Node-Google Cloud based ELK (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) application	May 2021

o Discovered an asteroid having a fixed orbit around Sun by analysing the data Pan-STARRS

# **Projects**

OCRed [OCR, Computer Vision, Python library, Research software, GH Actions, GH Pages]

August 2022

- o OCRed provides clever, simple, and intuitive wrapper functionalities for OCRing specific textual materials.
- The Python library has 1,400+ installs on PyPI, 10+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

ForMente [NLP, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Python, Firebase, Firestore, Heroku, GitHub Actions]

June 2022

- Using Natural Language Processing, ForMente lets you diagnose your feelings in the form of a secure personal diary.
- The NLP model is deployed on Heroku using FastAPI, and the app uses Firebase and Firestore as its backend.

ChaoticEncryption.jl [Image processing, Encryption algorithms, ODEs, PRNGs, Julia package]

February 2022

- Vectorised image encryption and PRNG algorithms that runs ~40X faster than ordinary nested-for implementations.
- The Julia package has 10+ installs on JuliaHub and 25+ stars on GitHub.

#### PDEsWithPINNs [PDEs, PINNs, Python, DeepXDE]

January 2022

- Worked under Prof. Shobha Bagai to solve 1, 2, 3, and 4D Partial Differential Equations using Physics-Informed Neural Networks.
- Worked with Neural tangent Kernels, Multi-scale Fourier feature networks, and Spatio-temporal Multi-scale Fourier feature networks to predict high-frequency details.

# Mentorship

## Google Summer of Code

May - September 2022

• Mentored students under PyBaMM, NumFOCUS, on projects involving, but not limited to, documentation, DevOps, parameterisation, and visualization.

CodePeak December 2021

• Mentored 10+ students in the field of open-source application development.

#### Relevant Skills

Languages: Julia | Python | C/C++ | Java | JavaScript | Dart

Frameworks/Libraries: Tensorflow | FluxML-Ecosystem | PyTorch | PyData-Ecosystem | SciML-Ecosystem | DeepXDE

Flutter | FastAPI | NodeJS

Platforms and Tools Linux | Android | Heroku | Google Cloud | Elasticsearch | Kibana | Firebase | Docker | CI/CD

Research Interests: Machine Learning | Scientific ML | Research Software Development | OSS Research Software

## Languages

Hindi (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (basic), Punjabi (conversational)